Leader, welcome back to the CAP Ideas
conference.
>> Morning. Great to be here.
>> Yeah, it's true a real honor for us to
have you here. Um I want to get into uh
what you have to live
a in a day day in and day out in the
current Congress, but I want to take us
to a happier place to begin with.
It's January 3rd,
2027. You've just been sworn in as
Speaker of the House.
See, they're already they're happy
already.
What uh what are the two or three big
things you're going to want to get done
for the American people when that
happens?
>> Well, thank you, John, uh for your
friendship and your leadership and
uh to Neera, so appreciate you and to
everyone here in the CAP uh family. It's
great to be back.
You know, I think
our focus
and we're going to continue to
relentlessly make this clear over the
next few months in advance of taking
back control of the House of
Representatives, and then when we do uh
in the next Congress, we want to focus
on cost, we want to focus on care,
and we want to focus on combating
corruption.
But, right at the top of that list
uh is the economy,
lowering the high cost of living,
dealing with the fact that far too many
everyday Americans are struggling to
live paycheck to paycheck, can't thrive,
and can barely survive. This in the
wealthiest country in the history of the
world, and it's unacceptable.
And the American people have been crying
out
uh for this administration or this
Congress
to do something about lowering the high
cost of living, and they failed.
And, you know, we define those costs in
a variety of different, you know, issue
areas that we have to tackle, housing,
right? Gas, groceries, goods,
and utilities.
In terms of what needs to happen,
you know, related to the impact uh that
this environment is having on everyday
Americans. Related to that, of course,
is care and the cost of it, but also
making sure that that care is provided
in a high-quality way. So, clearly
that's health care. We have a broken
health care system
that Republicans have decimated,
unprecedented attack on the health care
of the American people and all of the
things.
That's on Medicaid, of course, the
largest cut to Medicaid in American
history. The tax on hospitals and
nursing homes, community-based health
clinics, the Affordable Care Act,
vaccine availability, the National
Institute of Health, the Centers for
Disease Control, the FDA, all of the
things, unprecedented attack
on the health care of the American
people. We got to fix our broken health
care system and make sure that what we
put in place
is the best ever.
And then, of course, related to that
is child care on the front end
and elder care
on the back end.
And then,
we certainly feel a responsibility to
tackle
like the
just the naked corruption that we're
seeing.
But also connected to the fact that
because Republicans are focused on
enriching themselves, their family
members and their
big donors,
they're not focused on solving the
problems that the American people want
us to solve
on their behalf.
But there's a related issue,
excuse me, that we need to deal
that we need to deal with.
And that is
dramatic reform to the fact that the
system is rigged against everyday
Americans to benefit, you know, the
elites. And that's going to require
massive
campaign finance reform, massive
electoral reform, and yes, massive
Supreme Court reform as well.
>> I want to I want to I want to come back
to the court and I want in particularly
the Cali decision. Uh but I I noted uh
your current circumstances um and you're
having to live with a a in a house that
really is just on bended knee to the
president. Uh but you've been actually
been successful in peeling off
Republicans uh and passing uh by uh
using uh discharge petitions the uh
the premium tax credits uh the release
of the Epstein files uh the stock
trading ban for example speaking of of
uh corruption we've just seen the stock
trades of the president uh coming out.
Uh
How How's that worked? How have you
gotten Republicans to come over? Is it
just the political pressure of their
constituents or
and and is there any hope that you can
actually create some bipartisan
coalitions in the future?
>> Well, you know, we began um the Congress
understanding that we had two
responsibilities. One, we had to do
everything we can to push back against
the extremism that is being unleashed on
the American people.
Right? With righteous intensity
to push back against this extremism
devastating everyday Americans.
While at the same period of time
do as much as we can to govern in the
minority as if we were in the majority.
And in the house there are only limited
tools available
to accomplish that objective and the
discharge petition
where you can get
to 218
signatures on a piece of legislation and
over the objection of the president and
the speaker forcing up or down vote on
the floor of the House of
Representatives. We've now done that six
different times.
And
that
as far as we can tell, those six times
plus the two times that we did it in the
last Congress, eight, is more in those
two Congresses than at any other point
in the last 100 years in the House of
Representatives.
And so, we've had them on the run
legislatively, and these have been on
interesting issues.
As you indicated, John, in the aftermath
of
the 43-day government shutdown, where we
made the issue Right? We just said seven
consecutive words over and over and over
again, cancel
the cuts or I guess it was eight words,
cancel the cuts, lower the cost, save
health care.
And repeating save health care over and
over and over again, that was the fight.
And in the immediate aftermath of that
fight, the Republicans felt the pressure
of extending the Affordable Care Act tax
credits in the House on our terms. A
3-year straightforward extension, we
were able to do it. On Epstein, and
you'll hear from Robert, you know,
Garcia and the oversight Dems have done
a great job of standing with the Epstein
survivors and pushing for transparency
and accountability, and ultimately we
broke them on a discharge petition
with respect to Epstein. One of the
things that hasn't gotten a lot of
attention
is that in November or early December of
last year, uh we actually compelled 20
Republicans to join with us to override
one of Trump's first executive orders uh
that smashed
his executive order, collective
bargaining rights for over a million
federal employees. We passed legislation
through a discharge petition in the
House to override uh that executive
order. And then, of course, most
recently, we extended temporary
protected status for Haitian migrants.
Which was interesting because just 2
years ago, these very same Republicans
were claiming that these Haitian
migrants were eating cats and dogs
in Springfield.
And 2 years later, we forced them to
join with us to extend temporary
protected status
because it's the right thing to do.
So, I think what is demonstrated is that
on issue after issue after issue, when
we're on the right side of it, and when
we're disciplined, and when we're
focused, and when we put pressure in
particular on the so-called swing seat
Republicans, they have been breaking
with us to do the right thing for the
American people.
>> Yeah, it's a little bit different than
old school, you you get a little bit, I
get a little bit. It's really pressure
and focus.
Uh and that can happen on the
affirmative agenda as as well. You you
have anticipation that you that will
help actually move from ideas and and
control in the house to be able to get
stuff that actually gets signed, maybe
roll back the Medicaid cuts, uh get
those premium tax increases done. Uh
>> That's exactly right. And you know, what
I guess part of how we as House
Democrats view this moment, either MAGA
extremists are going to break the
country, or we're going to break them.
And our goal is to break them. We will
defeat them.
We have to beat them electorally, and
then we have to break their spirit
because of the extremism that's being
unleashed on the American people that's
completely and totally unacceptable. And
that's the approach that we've taken
with respect to legislating on these
discharge petitions.
>> Yeah, let me look uh
Let Speaking of extremism, uh let's talk
a little bit about redistricting. Uh
Trump started this off, tried to urge
all the uh MAGA state legislatures,
state legislative bodies, uh to
redistrict in in the middle of term.
Democrats have fought back. Uh in
California, we lost that Supreme Court
case in Virginia. Uh tried to uh really
uh push back, but I think we've now
created a cycle
uh that the American people must sit
back and and wonder about. Added to that
is this Calais decision, which gutted
the Voting Rights Act.
Uh they had done a lot already to weaken
the Voting Rights Act, uh endorse
extreme partisan redistricting, uh but
uh going forward, what's the strategy uh
to get a level playing field for the in
the in the elections?
>> Yeah, well, because of um
you know, the Republican gerrymandering
scheme had been a complete and total
failure with Democrats fighting back
aggressively until they were aided and
abetted by the Calais decision
and an egregious decision by the
Virginia Supreme Court 4-3 decision,
partisan decision, completely
unacceptable to overturn the will of
more than 3 million Virginia voters.
Now, we're still going to win two seats
minimum in Virginia, and then we're
going to work as hard as we can in
advance of 2028 to restore that 10-1 map
because that's what the voters uh
decided would be appropriate moving
forward. Now, notwithstanding, you know,
the Calais decision and what happened in
Virginia,
you know, our assessment is that the
Republicans may have netted, when it's
all said and done, in terms of what's
happening in the South right now, maybe
three or four seats in this environment.
Which means that they will go perhaps
from plus three, which is where we
started, narrowest majority that any
party has had in the Congress since
1930, the Great Depression,
uh to maybe plus six or plus seven. Keep
in mind, when we won the House back in
2018, and we're in a 2018 type of
environment right now, as poll after
poll, private and public, continue to
show,
if not better,
uh we needed to flip 24 seats, John, as
you recall.
With the help of many of the people in
this room and people all across the
country, we flipped 40.
31 of those seats were in districts that
Donald Trump had just won.
And so, we only need to flip a fraction
of those
even given all of the gerrymandering
that they've done,
aided and abetted by these two
Supreme Court decisions. We only need to
flip a fraction of those uh in order to
take back control of the House. And I
can tell you right now, as a guarantee,
we are taking back control of the United
States House of Representatives in
November.
But then our work is not done.
Um Republicans had a structural
advantage, which is why they launched
this gerrymandering scheme, because so
many of our states had commissions
built into the law or constitutional
impediments to being able to redraw
districts in this cycle
that have to be unwound.
And in most state legislatures,
California was an exception.
Uh it takes two consecutively elected
legislative bodies before you can bring
something before the voters or do it
uh
in the state legislature.
Uh which means that in states like New
York and New Jersey
and Washington and Colorado
and we'll add on top of that Oregon,
Illinois,
and Maryland,
we'll have at least seven states that we
believe we need to respond
in advance of 2028 uh to what they are
doing in the deep South to wipe out any
structural advantage that they're trying
to get themselves in advance of 2028.
And we'll have some opportunities
uh in legislative bodies across the
country where we're only one or two
seats short of a trifecta
uh to be able to explore
uh what can be done and we still have
pending
uh litigation in Wisconsin where we're
waiting on the Wisconsin Supreme Court
uh to act. And so, we look at this as a
two-step process.
Right? We'll finish the job in 2026.
We'll take back the house. And then
we've got uh to make sure in these
states all across the country, we'll
have a renewed opportunity to respond
because you'll have two consecutively
elected legislatures and many of these
places, like New York, they'll act in
the first instance this year and then
come back in January, early next year,
they'll act again.
And then we'll have new maps in these
states all across the country
uh to wipe away any advantage that they
may try to gain by going into further
states in the deep south.
>> Uh in the past, uh Democrats, not so
much in the house, but in the White
House and in the uh and in the Senate,
have been criticized for not focusing as
much on judges and the Supreme Court in
particular as the Republicans done.
Uh is there anything we can do about
that at this stage? If you anticipate uh
trying to uh find a way to uh either
through term limits or other ways to
reform the court, which has been just so
partisan, lowers its standing with the
American people?
>> Yeah, in my view, listen, all options
are on the table.
Uh
and, you know, that effort will be led
you know, by Jamie Raskin. No finer
constitutional scholar you'll find in
this country uh who will be the chair of
the Judiciary Committee.
Uh and the Democrats on the Judiciary
Committee as it relates to what needs to
be done
to ensure that we don't have
you know,
we don't have a Supreme Court that in
far too many instances,
they're operating like partisan
political hacks.
Right? Trying to advance
the interests of the Republican Party.
And by the way, we should take a step
back and Eric Holder had an op-ed today
where he laid out several of the things
that I think need to be on the table in
terms of Supreme Court reform.
Uh but perhaps the original
most recent sin from this Supreme Court
was granting
this president blanket immunity
which has given him the ability to
operate with impunity unleashing
corruption that we've never seen in the
history of the country. I mean, Donald
Trump makes Richard Nixon look like a
choir boy.
It's outrageous
and it's hurting the American people and
we're seeing it with the billion-dollar
ballroom. Now, we're seeing it with the
multi-billion dollar slush fund for
violent insurrectionists who brutally
beat police officers. And we're seeing
it with the more recent disclosures of
the stock trading ban. And when we talk
about cleaning up corruption, we want to
do it across the board. Our own
institution, the Supreme Court, which
needs an ethical code of conduct imposed
upon them.
And of course, you know, the White
House, which is a Trump cartel, an
organized crime entity
that is unfolding
in 1600 Pennsylvania Avenue. There's no
other way
to say it and the American people
know it. And we can start uh by
prohibiting the ability for members of
Congress
for the president and the vice president
and for Supreme Court justices to trade
stocks.
>> Right.
We're We're We're out of time, but I
just I want to give you a one shot at uh
Robert Garcia's going to be here uh
later. Uh but there's kind of a free
fire zone out there on oversight going
into a new Congress.
Uh what are the priorities? I think
maybe you just laid them out on the
corruption side. There's the war uh in
Iran. There's uh the bad policy
decisions.
How do you organize the house to
actually tell a story to the American
people?
>> Well, you know, I think our our
fundamental premise is that taxpayer
dollars should be used to make life more
affordable for the American people, to
improve their quality of life, not to
unleash
masked, untrained ICE agents to
brutalize or kill Americans as we
horrifically saw.
Not to fund a reckless and costly war of
choice that has increased, you know, gas
prices on the American people. And
certainly we shouldn't see taxpayer
dollars used, you know, to subsidize the
lifestyles of the rich and shameless who
are connected to Donald Trump, right? As
part of a friends and family plan that
he is
unleashed on the American people in real
time, hiding in plain sight.
And so I think in terms of our oversight
responsibilities in this corruption
piece,
I think it's the American people
intrinsically believe the system is
broken, is rigged, and is corrupt. What
we have to do is connect that corruption
to the fact that things aren't happening
here in Washington that they want to see
happen, right? Particularly driving down
the high cost of living. And the thing
I'll say about this, John, is in terms
of
Listen, our oversight effort, it's not a
democratic playbook. It's not a partisan
playbook. It's the James Madison
playbook. Like it was Madison who said
Congress at its best should be a rival
to the executive branch. He said it and
there were no political parties.
It was the American thing to do.
And of course, that's not what this
Congress,
you know, has done. They've just been a
reckless rubber stamp for Donald Trump's
extreme agenda. And I found it
fascinating when King Charles came
and spoke, crisp 20-minute speech that
he gave uh to the Congress and what
perhaps
the most memorable part is when he
referenced the Magna Carta
and talked about the Magna Carta as the
foundation for the principle
that executive power is subject to
checks and balances.
And every single Democrat
immediately got up and gave him a
standing ovation.
And then I looked over to the other side
of the aisle and much to my surprise, I
saw Republicans standing up
and giving him an ovation. And I'm
thinking to myself
don't they know King Charles is talking
about them right now?
But checks and balances, that's an
American thing. It's not a partisan
thing. It's a Madisonian
thing. It's It's the framers' vision
for what the Article 1 first amongst
equals branch of government should be.
And so while we have a responsibility to
drive down the high cost of living and
focus on the affordability agenda
we also believe
uh that there's an accountability agenda
that the American people uh will expect
rightfully
for a separate and co-equal branch of
government to pursue. You know, and led
by Robert Garcia who'll do a great job.
The oversight Democrats have already
done a great job. If you think about it,
in the minority
Kristi Noem is gone. We ran her out of
town.
And Pam Bondi is gone.
And if I have anything to do with it,
Pete Hoekstra will be next. Pete
Hoekstra will be next.
>> Um we've got to maybe get to one or two
questions from the audience that have
been uh submitted, but uh
one that's important, which is
uh and I'll just read the question,
which is the poll show American people
don't trust government institutions
anymore. I think that's particularly
true of young people. How do you restore
that sense of of uh uh
support, faith, that things can get
better, that government can be on your
side?
>> Yeah, no, it's incredibly important and
we have to deliver.
Right? We we're going to make
a series of promises as part of our
affirmative agenda
to the American people and then we got
to work as hard as we can
to bring those promises to life
in ways that tangibly
you know, will improve their quality of
life.
And young people are facing a very
uncertain environment. It was the case
prior to the rise of AI. Now with AI, it
even adds further
uh to that uncertainty and we got to run
straight into that uncertainty
and make sure that this generation
doesn't become the first one
where you can't clearly see
a better quality of life for them
uh as compared to the generations upon
whose shoulders they stand. You know, I
have the honor of serving
in the district that was once
represented by Shirley Chisholm. And
Shirley Chisholm, the great Shirley
Chisholm, she once said to some young
folks who were thinking about running
for office, "If you run for office,
don't be a career politician, be a
statesperson."
And they said, "What's the difference?"
And she said, "Well, a career politician
is only concerned with the next
election.
But a statesperson cares about the next
generation.
And we've got to make sure that we
deliver for this generation of young
people and future generations to come.
We say it, we feel it,
but we have to mean it
in terms of the actions that actually
occur to bring that to life.
Um and I think, you know, that's the
responsibility that we all shoulder.
Uh we know it's a heavy responsibility.
Uh but we plan on delivering like the
Democratic Party going all the way back
to FDR
has. We've done it before.
We've done it before. You're talking
about Social Security
and rural electrification and the GI
Bill and Medicare and Medicaid and Head
Start and the Civil Rights Act and the
Voting Rights Act and the Fair Housing
Act
and the Children's Health Insurance
Program and the Affordable Care Act and
the Inflation
Reduction Act and all the things that
were accomplished in the last
administration. Every single one of
those things brought to you by your
friendly neighborhood Democratic Party.
That's a pretty good track record of
success to stand upon.
And we've got to build upon that to
continue to deliver for the future.
>> I told you I was going to ask you
uh who's your hero in politics or in
life and then we're going to get out of
here.
You can pick which one.
>> Yeah. Well, I thought you were going to
actually ask me you know am I picking
the Knicks in five or in six games?
>> want to say when I
Uh
>> But um
>> Is there a Is there a question there?
>> Yes.
But I will I you know, I will say
>> I figured the answer to that was
obvious.
>> Well, that's right. Um I I I think
you know, there's so many legends that
I've had the opportunity to serve with
in this Congress. Of course, Nancy
Pelosi and Steny and you know, Jim
Clyburn.
But we all feel
like
a particular sense of pride and honor to
have served with John Lewis.
And he was a real American hero.
And
you know, I'll never forget
that when I was on the floor as a as a
new member of Congress, my first or
second day
saw John Lewis
call me over
and he asked me a question. He said,
"Are you the new guy?"
And I said, "Yes, sir, Mr. Lewis.
That's me."
He said, "Hakeem, you're a colleague of
mine right now. You don't have to call
me Mr. Lewis, you can call me John.
I said, "Yes, sir, Mr. Lewis, I
understand."
Then he asked whether I was from
Brooklyn, he thought I said, "Yes."
Um he said, "Well, you know, I I I hear
some good things about your class,
yourself." And I came in, there was 52
other 51, 52 other Democrats and great
Democrats.
But Washington D.C. can be a a tough
place.
So, young man, I don't want you to get
into any trouble.
Unless it's good trouble.
And he lived a life
of good trouble.
And he showed such character and courage
and conviction and belief in America,
the good of America, even when
confronting the ugly underbelly of
America.
And we certainly are called upon to
summon
that that type of courage and character
and conviction to get us through the
storm,
which we will get through this storm,
and make sure that we come out stronger
as a country on the other side of it.
John Lewis.
>> Thank you, Mr. Jeffries.
>> Thank you all.
>> Thank you, leader.